howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talk
about on the show
we now have links to books and articles
referenced in recent podcasts that are
available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to
jimrutshow.com
that's jimrutsshow.com
today's guest is daniel schmochtenberger
daniel's central interest is long-term
civilization design developing better
collective capacities for sense making
and meaning making to inform higher
quality choice making
towards a world commensurate with our
higher values
and potentials daniel was an early guest
on the show back in
ep 7 where we explored a wide range of
daniel's thinking all kinds of
interesting topics
if you're stimulated by this
conversation go check out ep number
seven
today we're going to be a bit more
focused talking about sense making
and we won't forget that sense making is
principally important due to its
relationship to decision making and
action taking so daniel welcome back
it's really good to be back jim thank
you for having me looking forward to the
discussion today
yeah i think it's going to be great and
needless to say it's highly timely
so why is sense making so important
right now
why i think sense making is always
important
is uh we can look at all of the object
level problems in the world whether
we're talking about environmental
problems
or war pathways to war or infrastructure
issues
as coordination issues why are humans
choosing the things they do and
particularly large-scale behavior
type issues and that if we want to solve
climate
change or wealth inequality or whatever
we have to have
humanity coordinating quite differently
the basis of large-scale
or collective choice making is
collective sense making
and our ability to communicate
effectively and
i think that for instance if we're
trying to solve climate change
and we're not looking at the attendant
issues that are associated say the
economic issues or the geopolitical
issues so we come up with a solution
that
say if the u.s and europe were to
implement a particular kind of carbon
tax and china wasn't and there was no
enforcement mechanism
it would have geopolitical ramifications
that are also very problematic
as long as the solutions we're coming up
with to problems
are based on that kind of partial sense
making then you'll have lots of people
who care about the thing that is being
harmed by the very partial solution that
is trying to benefit
one thing that actively resist it and
even if it's not that even if we had a
fairly good solution
but we didn't have high quality sense
making
generally where a lot of people didn't
understand the issues and we're against
it it's very hard to do anything at
scale
uh when you're fighting very high
friction of a lot of people disagreeing
and
not wanting to implement a particular
solution and right now i would say we're
kind of at
peak bad sense making where on almost
every consequential issue
either people have no idea what's true
or they're very fervent about what's
true
in total polar opposition to other
people that think
nearly opposite things and we see that
in the covid time with
mass squaring and hydroxychloroquine and
lockdowns that these got to the level of
massive civil tensions in the u.s and in
other places in the world
and the question of you know is covid
actually an exaggerated mostly hoax or
is it a
very serious pandemic is lockdown the
appropriate solution or is that
does that cause problems that are much
worse than it or
is systemic racism the biggest issue in
america or really a kind of non-issue
and what are chinese intentions with
regard to the world and how should u.s
relate to it pretty much across all the
the spectrum of all the most critical
issues there is
nothing like shared coherent sense of
what is true and what should happen
and so not only can we not solve any of
the problems but then the
inherent polarization of the different
views on it becomes its own
source of civil breakdown and so we're
watching a very rapid civil breakdown
right now
and if we can't do a better job of
getting people to be able to make sense
of the world in a more
coherent way and communicate in a more
effective way
then i think we see civil breakdown
continue to unravel
yep i'm afraid you're right a couple
points i'll toss in is
you mentioned scale and that's something
that i think is fundamental when we
think
about the problem and that the world is
now finally coupled on a global basis at
high density
that's really only been true since maybe
the 1980s if you look at the growth of
for instance trade
world trade previously peaked in 1914
and didn't recover to 1914 levels as a
percentage of gdp until the 80s
kind of a surprise but true of course
it's continued to grow since
and of course the globalization of
finance etc
and the fact that we are apparently at
or beyond the carrying capacity of the
earth for our civilization has made the
earth itself
a global player right and so those
things make the game
much more difficult hard enough to
coordinate in your family
right what are we going to watch on tv
tonight imagine trying to
have to coordinate at a global scale and
the other is as you alluded to
the high dimensionality or we could even
call it the complexity of the problems
that humanity is dealing
with these aren't like how do we make
iron into steel
more effectively and we come up with the
bessemer furnace you know that was a
kind of a narrow limited shot very big
innovation that made a big difference
for humanity but it's you know
pretty much one or two dimensions right
how to deal with climate change or
inequality
or how do pandemics spread on a globally
highly interconnected network
or problems of high complexity and
problems of high complexity
typically are not resolvable by formal
analytical methods because the
dimensionality of the space of
possibilities is too high right
we have to proceed by experiment by
heuristics
etc because there are no closed form
solutions there is no bessemer furnace
for solving climate change for instance
particularly not if we have to
address the various domains that you
mentioned the other and i think this is
somewhat underappreciated by many people
but clearly some of the experts
are starting to understand it is we have
stumbled into a communications
ecosystem that was not called for not
designed that it just emerged
right i'm old enough to remember when
there were three tv networks
and the typical american household
watched one of those three
at any given hour in the evening and
something like 60 or 70 percent of
americans
got their news from those three tv
networks
what's replaced that has been a
cacophony of voices
none of whom have any high status with
any high percentage of the population i
think the other day we were having a
chat
i looked up online that breitbart for
all of its
influence reaches about five million
unique people directly
per month so in the old days that would
have been considered a fringe network
but because of its ability to propagate
on these social networks and email and
talk radio
and all these coupled highly
fractionated networks we're living in an
unprecedented
information ecosystem and i think this
is a theme i'm going to come back to i'd
be interested to get your thoughts on it
that this communications ecosystem is
just what you'd think any ecosystem
would be
it's a platform for evolution and
stuff's evolving
very rapidly that's why i said it was
not called for it was not designed
it's just evolving you know no one
directed from on high for
zuckerberg to design facebook god knows
what exact reason he actually did it for
maybe it was just to get laid who knows
but it's ended up by good execution and
by being at the right place and right
time
to have created an unprecedented way for
people to communicate on a global basis
which we have no experience in dealing
with so
with those themes out there is ones that
i'd be interested in getting your
thoughts on is
global scale complexity and the fact
that we have an evolved
and radically new communications
platform
in which to try to do sense making yeah
okay we'll come back to the complexity
i'll start with the communications
platform
so interesting thing about human
communication is even if we're trying to
share true information it's hard to
decouple it from a gentic interest
so if i'm sharing something with you
you're taking it as something that could
inform your better choice
making but i'm also taking it as an
opportunity to influence your choice
making
in a direction that's possibly
beneficial for me so
lying is not a new thing people have
lied or at least just created spin or
marketing since
forever and you can read sun tzu
and see that the whole idea of narrative
warfare and info warfare is a
thousands of year old idea and that
people actually really crafted
how do you get deception right to win
war and run kingdoms and things like
that and then as the media technology
changed
the ability to do effective influence
uh increased obviously with the written
word you could scale a message much
further and then with the gutenberg
press and then with
you know various forms of broadcast and
then
whoever it is that controlled broadcast
has such an unprecedented influence over
the whole population there's so much
power to that
that those who are seeking to win at the
game of power seek to capture and
influence the broadcast and so we can
see that
when we look at like broadcast stations
being consolidated financially right now
by
murdock or koch brothers or whatever
that's that's also not new right you see
henry luce setting up the media empire
you know a century ago seeking to do a
similar thing let's own all the
magazines
so when even when you had that broadcast
scenario
there was manipulation that was involved
but from a social coherency point of
view when you as you mentioned when
there were three channels
it's pretty likely that even if what
everyone is seeing has some distortion
they're at least seeing the same thing
and so they can agree or they can
disagree and they did fervently
but they had some basis of shared
information about the world to agree or
disagree on because most of us have no
information
about most of the topics that we are
passionate about through direct
info we weren't in beirut we weren't in
wuhan we weren't in
dc or portland when the process happened
all of our beliefs about it
are being mediated to us by media and
in the current information environment i
can
find uh you know a trump supporter and a
biden supporter in two different parts
of the country
who can scroll their facebook feed for
10 hours and not necessarily see a
single piece of news in common even
though they're seeing news the whole
time
so there's basically no shared reality
basis for them to even be in reaction to
and
democracy just can't work in an
environment
where people can't have effective
conversations and they don't have any
shared base reality
and so we can see that in the u.s there
is no real
kind of sense of a who are our
countrymen where we feel some fealty
across for instance a left-right divide
at this moment
that creates national unity and the
ability to have something like a
democracy or republic or participatory
governance we have instead
so much internal enmity and in-group
out-group dynamics
that for the most part more enmity than
we have towards any external forces that
that's of course
driving the breakdown and lack of
coherence of that
system as a whole and so when we look at
the movement from
broadcast to internet and one of the
things we see is like
you were there you remember well there
was this kind of libertarian idea that
that would be awesome because it would
remove the ability of a few
people who held the monopoly on
broadcast to control the message
everyone could put out their own stuff
through youtube and
maybe the the best ideas would emerge to
the top which was like
a naive hopeful thing because
when so much content gets produced that
there's a billion search results for any
topic and no one
could even like it would take your whole
life just to go through the search
results for one topic
then of course how do we create
algorithms that curate all of this
content becomes the central topic and so
we see that with
the youtube recommendation algorithm and
the facebook news feed algorithm
massive machine learning indexing
technologies
that can actually sort through that and
then the question is what is their basis
to sort through the information and put
it in front of you
and when we had broadcast the tv
couldn't get a lot of information about
me directly so it had to have very
generalized kind of marketing it could
tell
more ratings or less ratings but when
i'm on my news feed and it can pay
attention to what i click on what i
share how long my mouse hovers over
things
by the time i've liked 300 things on
facebook the algorithm can predict what
i'm going to like better than my spouse
can
and then develop a psychographic model
of me that
is actually better than you know any
kind of psychologist psychographic model
of me could be
then it curates all the content to my
interest which in a way
but my interest in a very specific sense
because these platforms are businesses
that have their own agentic interests
and their agenda
interest is that they have a business
model that's based on selling
advertising
and they sell more advertising by
maximizing
user engagement mostly meaning time on
site also sharing and things like that
and most people don't plan i'd like to
spend
six hours on facebook today and their
life would be better if they got off and
went and did something else
so time on site is usually maximized by
getting people to not be in their
prefrontal cortex remembering what their
plans are
but to get hooked somehow so
how to put the content in front of me
that will maximally hook me
ends up being a combination of appealing
to emotional
triggers and cognitive bias when there's
so much information and i don't know
most of it
my relevance filters are going to pay
attention to the things i already know
are important which is going to have me
double down on bias
and the things that scare me or anger me
are worth more of my time for kind of
evolutionary protective reasons
so as there's so much content and
there's micro targeted psychographic
information about me
and it's curating that feed uniquely to
me not even to a demographic profile but
n equals one optimization
to maximize time on site for everyone
then everyone gets more bias and
everyone gets more emotionally hijacked
so you end up in a world where you have
not just
two competing points of view but
increasingly more fractured
narrative camps all of whom have less
shared venn diagram
overlap with each other and everyone is
both more certain
and more outraged while simultaneously
being more wrong because
the complexity is such that no one can
really do epistemology
people believe yes or no on climate
change or whatever the topic is and
almost nobody has tried to read all of
the data and model it themselves
so there's a kind of epistemic nihilism
of
i can't possibly really make sense of it
so if i can't make sense of it
there's almost more of an unconscious
move to a tribalism of like
who are the leaders that i want to be
led by and
who are the in-groups that i want to
identify with so this
environment this media technology in
particular
i think is destructive to shared sense
making
and to individual sense making in a way
that is totally unprecedented in the
history of the world and the
and the scale at which it happens and
then that environment
and that's not it's not that facebook is
trying to
make people more radically left or more
radically right that's a second order
effect that's an externality of it
trying to maximize their time on site
but using a profoundly powerful ai
to do so that's really effective at it
that has these very tight empirical
feedback loops
but as it's doing that and everyone is
kind of
getting more certain and more bias it
becomes easier for other actors that
want to move people in a direction to
just kind of push them further in the
direction they're already trending
and so then it becomes very easy for
other state actors or other kind of
you know non-state actors but that have
interest to be able to come and make the
right become more right make the left
become more left by just feeding them
more of the stuff that they're already
oriented to
going into the chat rooms and being able
to exacerbate certain types of dynamics
and so the narrative in infowarfare to
turn the enemy against itself becomes
radically easy
in that information ecology
indeed indeed yeah let me respond to
several different points you made which
are
good one you're right i've been doing
this since 1980 i worked for the source
the very first consumer online system
and i can tell you we all thought we
were doing great work for democracy and
that in the future everybody
have access to all the information they
need and democracy
would be better than it ever been before
how naive we were
on the other hand i would suggest that
there was a phase change that occurred
in the economics of online that actually
caused it to trend towards the direction
that you so vividly
outlined and that was prior to 2004-2005
most information sources on the internet
that were of any quality or depth
were paid and so there was an alignment
between the person that operated the
service and the user
to get you the most value as quickly as
possible and get you the hell off
because they didn't want to pay for your
time online which was also more
expensive in those days
around 2004 2005 the economics
changed such that platforms and
bandwidth became cheap enough
that you could actually fully fund a
service at scale by advertising alone
and suddenly the dynamic that you
described came into being where the
business model
wasn't in alignment with the customer
which is to provide them as much value
for as little time online as possible
but quite the opposite
the revenue source was tightly coupled
to time online
so now the platforms think of them you
know google
facebook twitter etc have a
overriding business incentive to
maximize
your time online and as you say you add
in the new capability to do group of one
micro targeting on what hooks you the
most what hijacks your attention
to keep you online for as long as
possible
and then to loop back with i guess you'd
call it dopamine hijacking
which is to provide the most vivid the
most insane
there's been a lot of work on the fact
that for instance that fake news which
is intentionally designed to be
high impact will spread five or six
times farther than true news on
a similar topic and we all know how easy
it is to get sucked into
you know violent arguments on the
internet rather than a thoughtful
discussion about the pros and cons of
a piece of literary fiction and so again
these were not
designed in the sense that someone said
i think we should hijack people's
dopamine
to make them feel bad about themselves
and their neighbors
so that we can have a great business it
went step by step
in kind of a natural evolutionary way
from the introduction of fully
advertising based products in the
2004 and 2005 time frame
and now we get to the next step which i
haven't seen that much about yet
if we have a system based on dopamine
hijacking
if you know anything at all about drug
addiction
or not so much addiction but you know
the adverse effect of certain illegal
drugs
there's the concept of dopamine
exhaustion you know why do
people who inject amphetamines day after
day eventually go insane and see their
life fall apart
it's because of dopamine exhaustion
dopamine no longer sends a meaningful
signal you build up a tolerance
and you end up in despair
you know a exponential uprise because
one of the results of this kind of
dopamine hijacking platform is
dopamine exhaustion and the related
despair
so i thought i'd put those things in and
then again
just sort of point out maybe name
something the fact that non-state actors
and people who are operating in bad
faith can use the same tools that
evolved
for advertising i think about that it's
the affordances of the platforms and
again
if we think of the platforms as
evolutionary contexts
one of the things that starts to shape
what gives life
in an ecosystem are the affordances i.e
what can be done
so once you have micro targeting that
was designed for
you know rather mundane you know trying
to sell you a stereo that you don't need
or a slightly fancier version of ketchup
or something
those same affordances can now be used
for ways they probably were not
anticipated in originally
you know for non-state actors or state
actors or political actors of any sort
so again step back a little bit and
think about the ecosystem
and the evolutionary context in which it
provides
so yeah it's actually worth just taking
a moment on this topic of hypernormal
stimuli and dopamine
to just simplify radically dopamine
is a molecule associated with
motivational networks other things as
well pattern matching and things that we
would have motivation but kind of
feels good do it again type dynamics and
so
the things that give dopamine hits
evolutionarily are things that also
would confer
a collective advantage and so
let's say in a natural hunter-gatherer
environment pre-agriculture
most of you know human evolutionary time
has been it was pretty hard to get salt
it was pretty hard to get a lot of fat
pretty hard to get sugar because
you know a small amount of berries lean
meat and so
salt fat and sugar conferred
evolutionary advantage because
of caloric density and electrolytes to
make it through famine
so there was a increased dopamine hit on
that over
say leafy stuff uh that was quite
abundant
but didn't have the same kind of caloric
density obviously salt doesn't have
caloric density but the other ones
and so those people who uh
worked hardest to get those things would
have made it through more so there would
have been
also a selection for kind of strong
dopaminergic response to that
but that was evolutionarily useful in a
time where it was very hard to get those
things so then
we move forward to modern environments
where we can make fast food that is just
combinations of salt fat and sugar
and like run the experiments for maximum
palatability make it not
stuff that doesn't require chewing too
much and we get obesity epidemics
because the dopaminergic dynamics
haven't changed but they're no longer
evolutionarily adaptive now they're
actually
anti-adaptive and so we basically
extracted the dopamine part from the
associated evolutionary context and the
kind of nutrient part and now that
creates
a its own kind of catastrophic risk and
what fast food is to food
and nutrition is the same thing that
porn is to sexuality and relationship
take something that has a normal
dopaminergic process associated with
something that has evolutionary
advantage for
raising kids and bonding and etc
and just extract the hypernormal stimuli
parts devoid of any of the things that
would actually be
relevant to human life and the same is
true for what social media relationships
are to
social dynamics and relationships in
general
and we can see that from a kind of
marketing perspective or from a business
perspective
every business owner wants to maximize
the lifetime value of the customer and
maximize the number of customers
and addiction is a really good way to
maximize the lifetime value of a
customer
and so from the supply side figuring out
how to get marketing that manufactures
demand
and even to the point of manufacturing
addiction is a straightforwardly
profitable thing
and so we can see a mcdonald's or a
hostess or a
phillips morris or whatever could do
that well in the domain of chemistry but
now we have dopaminergic hits that are
just as powerful as that that are photon
mediated rather than chemically mediated
can be sent out to everyone can be
personalized to them
based on empirical feedback and that we
can start giving
kids with the screens that they're
looking at and touching
as children um and not control in the
way that we would control for you have
to be 18
for a cigarette or 21 for alcohol or
whatever else
so i think understanding
our susceptibility to hypernormal
stimuli and
the perverse incentives to optimize
hypernormal stimuli
and then for each company on its own to
optimize hypernormal stimuli but then
for
a company that is a curator of other
things
where its motive is to maximize your
engagement and your engagement with all
the things that are maximally sticky for
you maximize your engagement for it in
total
and to really get that the kind of
machine learning ai that's running the
facebook algorithm or the google youtube
algorithm is a more powerful ai than the
one that beat kasparov
chess that that is maximizing for
hypernormal stimuli across every axis
for you that it can in the platform
it's an important piece of context to
understand and for us to really think
seriously about how do we
as individuals and parents and whatever
create
be cognizant of that and create some
resilience and protection to it
factoring how
profound it is and as a society how do
we start to
remove the perverse incentive for
hypernormal stimuli because
when we talk about what is a healthy
civilization what are the right indices
we know it's not just gdp per capita
i would say one of the inverse indices
is addiction the more addiction a
society has the less healthy it is writ
large
and so this is a this is a meaningful
part of the conversation
yeah i think that's a very deep insight
i don't think i've ever heard it
described quite that way but a measure
of addictive behavior across
all modalities is actually kind of a
measure of anti-sovereignty
yeah exactly that's actually deep i'm
actually going to think about that for
a second at least in the background but
while i'm processing it in the
background
i also want to kind of go to slightly
different direction which is you know
the result of all this
one of the results is fragmentation and
destruction of all authority or at least
any consensus about authority
and replacing it with nothing so far at
least
but it's also worth remembering that the
good old days weren't necessarily so
good
remember there was a book called the
best and the brightest talking about the
really smart people that worked in the
johnson and kennedy administrations of
course the title was meant to be ironic
because those best and the brightest led
us into the idiotic quagmire the vietnam
war
right and one of the problems with too
much agreement
is not enough checks and balances in our
sense-making
and people who think that the best and
the brightest can march us right off a
cliff
i think that's worth keeping in mind too
so how to deal with this new emergent
world where there is no authority and
it's been replaced by nothing
probably we don't want to replace it
with a single
definitive authority the status quo that
was so powerful
in the top heyday of broadcast say 1965
seems as close as any of the high water
mark let's see what other comment that i
want to have on that uh oh the other is
that of course
this network world that we've created
that has emerged i think again i can
continue to
say that nobody planned this thing it
just emerged co-evolved
in a game theoretic sense with a bunch
of players that were operating
around maximizing money on money return
in the context of
what is technologically and economically
possible has resulted in a lot of good
things
we have now high dimensional exploration
of the design
space of possible alternative
civilizations
people i have on my show the
peer-to-peer network people in fact i
have michelle
bauwens coming on tomorrow again for the
second time you know
regenerative ecology people political
metamodernism
like hansey frynack who i've had on
three times actually
did the third episode last week and
it'll be out in a couple of weeks and
even our game b project which both of us
have been involved with
at various times so we should also
always keep in mind that this
wide open information ecosystem provides
a substrate for good
as well so when we're thinking about
interventions to
down regulate the bad we also have to
make sure that we don't
eliminate the good at the same time okay
this is
yeah this is very interesting um i'll
address the authority
part first and then the things getting
better and worse and how we'd address
that
the reason we don't want a single
monolithic authority on what is true is
the same reason
we don't want a single top-down world
government
is because we don't trust anybody with
that much power and we shouldn't
um and so one of our best ways of
dealing with the corrupting
nature of power is to at least keep it
in check with other powers
and so this is one of the reasons why
free speech issues are so tricky
is should speech be
absolutely free meaning
should we not bind any kind of speech
and we we know that like
libel and slander and yelling fire in an
open building and fake bomb threats are
problematic enough things that we
actually want to regulate them in some
way
but what about in an environment where
the original
considerations around free speech in
this country
were in a time where at most if i was
going to say something that was
not true and dangerous i might be able
to have a couple hundred people hear it
in a town hall and somebody else could
get up and talk i couldn't have it
scale to millions or billions of people
through kind of viral type dynamics
and so in a situation where the things
that actually appeal to bias
and emotional hijack will get up
regulated
in a way that they could never have been
before
based on the the algorithms and the
platforms free speech
there's a such a different
consequentiality around the wrong
information
so it'd be very tempting to say okay
well we should have fact checkers or
something like that but then the problem
becomes who is the arbiter
of what is actually true and what is not
true and is there anyone that we would
actually trust with that power
and i would say like a way that i think
about it
going back in time as you were
mentioning to previous
administrations where we have a
government authority that is going to be
the arbiter of truth in an area or
um you know academia or going back to
when it was the church is whenever
something becomes
the legitimate authority on truth for a
topic
it's extraordinarily powerful because
what everyone else thinks is real which
is the basis of how they're going to
behave
is actually like at the bottom of the
stack of power
and so even if a legitimate authority
emerges
rightly because it's actually earnest
and doing better
empiricism and whatever as soon as it
starts to get that power
there will be maximum incentive for all
of the power players to try to corrupt
it and influence it
in various ways which they usually can
because which science is going to get
funded is
is going to be based on someone who has
funds putting money into something that
will continue to
support or advance them having funds and
so
even if say a piece of science is
technically accurate it's not wrong it
might be that only certain topics within
a domain that have
roi more associated get funded other
ones don't like for instance
you know patentable small molecules and
pharma compared to
peptides or biologics or plant-based
things
and so then the preponderance of
research doesn't actually map to the
overall space
well so even things that are true can
still be
misrepresentative or misleading so this
problem of
that legitimate authority within a
economic game theoretic environment
will always get captured or influenced
to various degrees
and so how do we address that yep i
think that's getting damn close to the
center of the problem and
as people listen to podcasts no i
consider myself a madisonian
james madison the somewhat neglected but
my mind
deepest of all the founding fathers who
set up our system of checks and balances
probably not quite the optimal system
for the 21st century
but his fundamental belief was sooner or
later
you're going to have bad people capture
the levers of power and you better
build that into your design or you'll
regret it you know in the same way
when you talk about one world government
number of my friends think we should
have
a world government and i say uh when we
have five planets then i'll be
okay with having a world government so
if one of them up there'll be
four others to recover and to provide
alternative models for each other so
again a
very very very important design
characteristics i wanted to say one
thing on the one world government
we need to have governance i'm going to
separate governance as a process in
government as
a established top-down enforcement of
rule of law with monopoly of violence
we need to have governance at the level
that we're having effects
meaning we have to be able to actually
make sense of the effects we're having
and factor that into the choices that
we're making
and when we have planetary effects on
the atmosphere and the ocean
and etc but we don't have planetary
governance
then we just get multipolar traps where
okay we don't want to fish all the fish
out but if we can't make an agreement
that china or somebody else is going to
also follow
and they're going to get ahead
economically and the ocean's still going
to get ruined then they're going to use
that economic benefit to damage us not
only
will we not make an agreement to manage
the commons we actually have to race to
fish all the fish out faster than they
do
or make ai weapons faster than they do
or whatever else it is it's exploitive
and so not having global governance when
we're having global effect leads to
catastrophe
but having global government of the
types that have only ever become
corrupted and then as a result
broke down also leads to catastrophe and
so we need something
that is different than either of those
things that have been imagined so far
i think that's pretty much bang on or we
need to be very clever
in creating emergent networks that
essentially produce coordination
without actually having mechanisms of
governance
and that's a fairly subtle job but as an
example i think you actually mentioned
it somewhere
earlier suppose china doesn't conform to
carbon neutrality and the rest of the
world does the rest of the world could
use
massive tariffs on implicit
carbon to stifle trade from china
until they do come along so there's a
way to essentially set up a signaling
system
in which we get the coherent behavior
without actually having
formal institutions of governance or
mechanisms of governments so again
that's at least one area to think about
a little bit
we talk about free speech and this is
you know something we really do have to
think about again
as a madisonian there's a reason the
first amendment is the
first one in the u.s constitution and i
do believe that
free speech is hugely important and that
giving large powers the ability to
suppress speech
is dangerous but nonetheless
i think there's at least one line that i
think most of us can agree on
and unfortunately this is what's
propagating most rapidly now on the nets
and that is speech that is made in bad
faith
i actually remembered something that you
said about
what is good faith and i'm going to read
this back to you and maybe you can react
to it
that there is a correspondence between
the signal that you're communicating to
me
and what you believe is true
that strikes me as a good definition of
good faith
and yet we have you know people like the
russians meddling in our elections or
the oil companies putting out false
narratives about climate change
which seem pretty clearly to be bad
faith discourse
and it strikes me that bad faith
discourse
is to the mimetic sphere what pollution
is to the ecosystem
and that if there were a way to detect
bad faith discourse
that would be the first line to draw
yeah i mean yes and it's tricky i would
say
that the information ecology is polluted
both intentionally by what you call bad
faith discourse where someone is sharing
something they know
isn't true and unintentionally where
people are sharing something they think
is true that's just really wrong
and both of those end up damaging the
information in epistemic commons
but how do i who's going to then be the
arbiter of what is actually true
and how do i know what someone else's
actual intent was
maybe if i find a whole paper trail that
shows
that that person knew the thing wasn't
true and was
you know setting the thing up as a psyop
sure but oftentimes it's very hard to
prove intent
especially when the actors are hidden
behind
several layers of sock puppets so
so now we have to say okay well is it
about a
judge or some kind of centralized
authority that should be able to tell
if something's bad faith or not or is it
about increasing the collective
intelligence that is aware of and
sensitive to these things where everyone
is doing it
and those things simply don't trend in
the same way
and this starts to get into the
the kind of answer and theory of change
that i'm particularly focused on these
days
is we have this system you know a
republic or a democratic type system of
participatory governance
that wants everyone to be able to
participate in governance rather than
just be ruled by one or a few people
and if we look from the beginning
of what we call civilization we exclude
dunbar number tribes because it's a very
different phenomena
very few civilizations since the
beginning of civilization until now have
been republics or democracies they've
almost all been
feudalistic or autocratic of some kind
and that actually makes sense because
one guy ruling everything or some very
small number of people that can talk
coming up with a consensus
and then being able to rule is way
easier than getting a huge number of
people
mostly who are anonymous to each other
to all
actually be able to make sense of the
world and coordinate like a large number
of people coordinating is actually a
very expensive tricky thing
and from the way i see it throughout
history the few times
democracies emerged they emerged
following cultural enlightenments that
had a few things in common
when we look at the athenian democracy
coming out of the greek enlightenment
stoicism plus the aristotelian school
and you know a few things had caught on
to the place where they had a cultural
value around education
that everyone would learn formal logic
and everyone would learn
uh rhetoric and history and you know
those types of things
plus the kind of stoic culture where
they're all learning emotional
regulation
and the socratic method where they're
learning how to take each other's
perspectives debate any side of a
conversation well if i have a bunch of
people who are trained to be able to
assess base reality clearly on their own
they have emotional regulation so they
are not as susceptible to emotional and
cognitive hijacks and groupthink and
have the courage to disagree and things
like that
and they can take each other's
perspective and they're actively seeking
to
well those are the prerequisites to
something like
democratic system being able to emerge
because those people can have a good
quality conversation about shared sense
making
recognize that some compromises to agree
are better than warfare with each other
and come up with
solutions so collective choice making
emerges out of the collective sense
making meaning making and conversation
ability
and our country similarly coming out of
the post-european renaissance
enlightenment phase
was you know the idea of
renaissance men renaissance people who
could have expertise across a lot of
topics not just be specialists because
specialists
across different domains have a hard
time being able to communicate really
effectively towards governance that
requires looking at a lot of those
things but the idea that we could become
renaissance people that we could all
have empirical
capacity the scientific method and the
hegelian dialectic that we could hear a
view
and then seek the antithesis to that c
thesis and then seek a synthesis some
higher order reconciliation
that again gives rise to the possibility
of participatory governance and you can
see
when you read the documents and the
letters of the founding
fathers and of course there was a lot
wrong with the athenian democracy and a
lot wrong with our country that had
genocide and slavery as parts of its
origin but the whole world
had genocide and slavery as parts of
what were going on at the time and it
was at least moving in the direction of
increasing participatory
uh style governance the thing that the
founding fathers talk about
so much is the need for
very high quality universal public
education and very high quality fourth
estate that's independent or news as the
prerequisites of democracy
george washington said i'm not going to
quote exactly it's something to the
effect of that the
single most important goal of this
government should be the
comprehensive education of every single
citizen in what he called the science of
government
and i think the science of government is
such an interesting phrase because we've
separated science and humanity so
formally and the science of government
would be history and game theory and
political theory and the things that
people need
to know the shenanigans that happen so
that they can prevent them
and franklin said if i could have a
government without news or news without
a government i would take news because
if the people really know what's going
on
they can self-organize and overthrow
government if the people don't know
what's going on they can only be
captured
and our our public education or
education of any kind here in the kinds
of civics that people would need to
really understand what's happening in
government and understand
regulatory capture and be able to bind
it obviously is
close to non-existent and the news has
been mostly captured by
economic and political interests so
there is no chance for a bunch of people
that
identify as being in almost tribal
warfare with each other
who aren't sense making reality well who
don't understand governments who don't
really understand
markets who only have pejorative
strawmans of each other and don't seek
each other's opinion those people can't
do a republic or democracy so it will
simply devolve back to an autocracy
which we see happening
and the way i think of it is like if
there's a bodybuilder has a huge amount
of muscle the moment they stop working
out they start losing it because it's
very expensive metabolically to keep
that much muscle they have to kind of
keep working at it
it's very expensive to keep an entire
population comprehensively educated and
actively engaged
and once it seems like the government's
working well and a generation passes and
the kids didn't go through the pain of
the revolutionary war and the grandkids
didn't it
it becomes very easy to just get engaged
in your own stuff and not keep
participating in the governance
and then you stop having a government of
for and by the people and you start
having a
class of people that do government and
when
the people stop checking the state the
state stops being able to check the
predatory aspects of the market which is
what it's really intended to do
and then the market ends up capturing it
you get regulatory capture and then
rather than liberal democracy you get a
kleptocracy that eventually becomes an
autocracy
and that's what i see that we have right
now and so
do i trust any particular authority to
arbitrate truth or
good faith or whatever right now no do i
trust a collective intelligence that's
actually increasing in its authentic
intelligence
i would trust that much more it's an
expensive hard proposition
but i don't see any other good choices
yeah and i i think i agree with you a
key part of my own thinking that's been
formulating over the last year or two
is that as we talked about earlier we
live in an era of scale and complexity
which is completely unprecedented
in human affairs and i think it's
reasonable to assert
that the combination of scale and
complexity has made the ability for an
individual person to make sense
no matter how smart and educated they
are inadequate to the task
at hand i read a lot i know a lot i've
been
through a lot but i don't feel myself
confident at
all to make certain kinds of decisions
and nor in this
era of informational nihilism is it easy
to find
in who the right people are to make
these decisions that's less true
if you do some work you can find people
who actually know more than you do
and so i'm wondering if the you know
founding fathers
enlightenment view that we can bring
everybody
up to the level to be able to make good
sense
in high complexity and high scale is
realistic
or whether we ought to be thinking about
new institutional structures
i've been informed quite a bit in the
last year by the writings of hansey
frynack
in his political metamodernism two very
good books the
listening society and the nordic
ideology and he makes the distinction
between hierarchical complexity you can
think of that as kind of
mental capacity and code which is our
institutions and operating systems and
you know he'll admit when you push him
and i've pushed him some in interviews
that
hierarchical complexity can only be
moved a little bit in any one generation
while code can be moved quite a bit very
substantially
we have things like the french
revolution or the russian revolution
where
totally new codes were developed not
necessarily always for the better
but code is much more malleable than
hierarchical complexity
and so maybe in addition because i do
agree we absolutely have to upgrade
the education and thinking tools for
people
but may not we also have to think
carefully about new institutions
that take into consideration the fact
that we're dealing with unprecedented
complexity and scale
and what i've talked about a fair amount
i continue to believe might be an answer
is so-called liquid democracy where
instead of
myself having to become a good enough
expert on
30 different domains to make some form
of decision about it i can
proxy my vote to someone who i believe
knows more than i
do and is aligned with me on values and
then
under liquid democracy that person can
reproxy the same way
and so that the preponderance of our
decision-making power at least in the
political realm
gets concentrated towards more informed
people
and yet people who are still aligned
with us on values
and of course the other nice thing about
liquid democracy is to degree you
believe that one of your
people holding a proxy is no longer
doing a good job for you
you can change your proxy at any time or
you could reclaim it and just for a
single issue if you want
while i may you know proxy my defense
vote to my
uncle who was an air force colonel i may
choose to hold for myself the question
on whether we should go to war in iraq
or not
and i'm thinking that code may be more
malleable
than actual individual human
hierarchical complexity
so in terms of exploring how much can we
change at the level of the individual
how much at the level of the
communication protocols for collective
intelligence and how much at the level
of the
actual types of um shared
choice making systems that might be
different than just kind of current
representative democracy
what we're talking about here is the
context because we've set the context of
the damage to the information ecology
but we're also talking now about the
increased complexity of the issues
and i think we should actually just
build out the understanding of that
problem a tiny bit more
because it affects the way i think about
it the solution
is all right absolutely because you
brought this up at the beginning and i
wanted to come back to it
so partly it has to do with scale
for sure which is the
the founding fathers thing here there
was an idea that everybody could go to
the town hall
and discuss the issues that were mostly
geographically
close to them that everyone could sense
based reality on their own
and you could have a small enough number
of people in the town hall that for the
most part the people who had something
to say could actually say something
about it
and when we moved to a place of
most of the issues are globalized
whether we're talking about finance or
supply chains or environmental issues or
um you know geopolitical ones obviously
that's a level of complexity where
people
can't depend on their own base sense
making and they can't process that much
information and second and third order
effects and
confounding effects as well and one
topic i'll just enter here because we
haven't discussed it yet is the concept
of hyper objects
which is connected to but a little bit
distinct from just raw complexity
that we evolved to be able to apprehend
and understand
objects that were available to our
senses
and when i'm talking about something
like climate change i can't see
climate change i can't taste it i can't
hear it i can only conceptualize it
i can see a drought i can see a fire
there have always been droughts and
fires but to understand climate change i
have to think about some kind of
statistics and complex mathematical
models on the droughts and the fires
i also can't see world hunger i can see
a hungry person somewhere but i can't
actually
directly apprehend i can only do it
conceptually which also means i don't
have the same felt visceral experience
of the things
and the same is true with i can't
actually directly see or apprehend ai
risk or
biotech risk or nanotech risk or or the
nature of markets
and so we have a world where the most
influential things are mostly all not
apprehendable to the senses
and so we have not just the issue of can
we
have a better felt sense or our
intuitions are more right that our kind
of sensibility of what's likely true
as well as our kind of formal analytic
thinking
can we get hyper objects but then can we
get the connection of lots and lots of
hyper objects markets interacting with
social media environments interacting
with climate and
things like that and i think it's just
important to kind of state that
to have a sense of how different the
problem space of the things that we need
to understand and think about are now
compared to the evolutionary problem
space most people had to think about
and how different the kinds of
collective sentence making
need to be and choice make need to be
and then i'll also step back and say
even in environments where we weren't
dealing with as much in the way of
complexity and hyper objects
our sense-making was actually usually
still adequate to solve local problems
in ways that very often
caused other problems somewhere else or
down the road and
this is an important part of
understanding this is like the model
that we can look at all of our problems
as a result of either
conflict theory or mistake theory
conflict theory meaning we know we're
going to cause harm somewhere and we're
doing it anyways for game theoretic
purposes mistake theory
as you were mentioning with facebook we
didn't know this was going to happen and
it was simply an
unintended externality so we have to
deal with both
moving forward how do we remove the
basis of conflict theory so no one is
motivated to do things that will
knowingly
harm something else and how do we also
deal with the mistake theory of being
able to
anticipate externalities and internalize
them into the design processes better
and so the mistake theory side
you can go back to we didn't necessarily
know that the development of stone tools
would lead to us becoming apex predators
that were increasing our predatory
capacity faster than the environment
could become resilient
that led us starting to extinct species
at scale and then become
the apex predator in every environment
and start the anthropos
scene or you can come to a closer one
and say
when we were making the internal
combustion engine to solve the problem
of the difficulty of horse husbandry
pulling buggies
we didn't anticipate that in solving the
horse husbandry problem that we'd be
causing
climate change and oil spills and wars
over oil in the u.s petrodollar
and so typically if we're going to make
a solution that solves a problem
the solution has to be somehow bigger
than the problem
faster whatever to be able to scale and
overtake it to really solve the problem
but if the we define the problem in
terms
in a narrow way there's one or two or
some small number of metrics and the
solution we're trying to create
has a first order effect on a small
number of known metrics
but it might have second and third order
effects on a very large number of
unknown metrics
we can see that the safety analysis is
actually harder in kind
than the solution analysis and this is
something that we actually have to start
factoring
is i don't just need to understand the
problem i'm trying to solve i have to
understand the problem embedding
landscape of the adjacent problems and
the adjacent topics and the adjacent
meaningful things
and i have to start thinking through
second and third order effects better
whether i'm designing a proposition
or designing a piece of technology or
designing a company to solve a problem
to say if that effective
what other things is it likely to do and
what
harms could that cause to complex
environments and then how do we actually
factor that into the design process
yeah all true but how the hell do you
get
a human to actually be able to process
at that
level and again the humans aren't going
to get smart enough to do that none of
us can do that
right and so the answer has got to be as
you keep pointing to some form of
collective sense making
and collective decision making that's
high fidelity and in congruence with
reality
i think i mean i don't feel any sense
that education
plus a better child-rearing environment
at home is going to get anybody to be
smart enough to deal with
that constellation of issues well so
notice as you said that
you know you and i are probably more
oriented to try to sense make the world
an
average population and and have better
educational resources
but still can't make sense of everything
but you also notice that when we talk
i know that you know things that are
important that i want to know that i
don't and vice versa so i'm actively
seeking to try to understand your
your opinion um and so there's a there's
an interesting balance that is important
to understand that
is that one of the dispositions beyond
empiricism that orients towards
the capacity for collective sense making
to emerge
i'm neither oriented for agreeability
nor disagreeability
with you because i'm actually oriented
towards
respect relationally but then also
respect
to reality objectively so there's like a
intersubjective and an object of respect
so
my object of respect for reality is i'm
not going to agree with you if you're
wrong but i'm also not going to listen
to you where you might be right
and so i want to listen in good faith
seek to understand what you understand
push back where that's relevant not
because
i have a disagreeable personality and i
want to push back or have an agreeable
personality and i want you to agree
but because i care about what is true
enough and i'm in good faith with you
enough that we can seek
better understanding together so the
enlightenments that i'm talking about
are not just people being able to have
better objective sense making
but also better intersubjective capacity
that leads to higher quality
conversation so that collective
intelligence can start to emerge
so you're mentioning being able to find
somebody that knows
and and first let me just say before we
discuss
a perfected system we can just discuss
how to stop some of the most egregious
things about the current system
current system people are radically
certain about things that they have no
basis to be certain about
and it's actually their false certainty
that causes most of the problems if they
simply acknowledge that it was too
complex and they didn't know
they at least wouldn't be going to war
over dumb stuff
and to so to simply be able to have
people be like i don't know yet but i'm
interested and i'm gonna try to seek to
know better would actually slow the rate
of breakdown
tremendously uh yeah i believe i believe
that the phrase
i don't know is one of the most
important phrases
in in human collaboration it's
interesting when you read scientific
papers
the word it is not yet known appears at
high frequency and the better the
science the more frequently it appears
right this is one of the things that is
a value i really want to have come
across
as people having a mature relationship
to the topic of certainty and i think
it's easy to
get it wrong in both directions which
you know
a disposition to want to be more certain
because either i think the certainty
gives me security or
i seem smart or something like that just
makes us bad sense makers and makes us
dangerous
um and so uh the
fear of uncertainty and the desire for
excessive certainty
um excessive meaning more than the
desire for certainty that has us jumped
to it before we've done the right
epistemic process
is dangerous but the compensation
right there's a kind of postmodern trend
that takes any certainty is probably
some kind of imperialism
and only holding uncertainty is virtue
also doesn't give the basis to act so
what i want is to say
i'm comfortable being certain and my
certainty will never be a hundred
percent but it might be 99.9
depending upon how much experimentation
i've done relative to the thing the fact
that it's never a hundred percent means
that i'm always open to
the possibility that there's data i
didn't factor that's important
but i also need enough certainty to act
where inaction is also consequential
so factoring that action and inaction
have consequence and i have an ethical
binding
both to the quality of my action and the
results of my inaction
then i want to say well how do i get
enough confidence to make the right
choice for this particular thing
factoring the consequentiality of the
thing
and do i want to be comfortable with
uncertainty
and i want to be comfortable with
relatively higher certainty through the
right epistemic process that informs
right action
absolutely and i would also say that the
very important one that you mentioned
that most people
do not build into their sense making the
decision making
is the cost of inaction you know and i
had a
a long and interesting and fun business
career and i think i was more successful
than most and one of the reasons was i
very carefully calibrated about that
how much information how much certainty
did i need to pull the trigger
you know if this was something where if
you don't decide you're then you
decide when you're at
40 because the alternative is worse
there are many times when you're at 52
you should pull the trigger because
frankly the downside isn't that bad
maybe you'll lose some money so what
if the stakes were higher maybe it's 60
percent so anyway
to calibrate how much certainty you need
to pull the trigger
is one of the great skills of decision
making which is not taught
by anybody that i've ever seen i
fortunately was able to sort of pick it
up by
getting my mba with real bullets so to
speak in the real business battlefields
but if we made that part of our you know
education and epistemology
that by itself would be huge right and
of course it would totally attack the
fundamentals of american politics
in which it's always the right thing to
do to kick the can down the road
not confront it no matter what the costs
are for kicking the can down the road
yeah now this is a tricky thing is
there's
almost a a negative gradient problem
here where the people that do
less good thinking come to certainty
faster
and then make actions faster so
if someone doesn't want to make the
wrong kinds of choices
so they want to actually do deeper sense
making first
then if someone takes that too far
they're just seeding the control of the
world to people with the worst sense
making in the most action bias
and yet that doesn't we don't want a
multi-polar trap where everyone just
says okay i'm pretty sure i'm right so
i'm going to go for it
um so this is why that balance of there
is
responsibility for inaction as well as
action
and different things have different
consequentiality like what confidence do
i need that this is going to be a better
recipe to experiment with how much spice
i put in the food not that much because
at worst i ruined the meal but how much
confidence do i need
that a particular application of ai
is actually a good one for the world
well it should be a
ton higher confidence based on much
better processes of looking at
second third order effects because the
consequence is so high and the
and the reversibility might be so low
and this is where we're in a situation
where there are market
incentives to be first uh mover
which means to move as fast as possible
in some of the areas of highest
consequence where we should actually be
moving
slow and doing really good safety
analysis and um
yeah that's that's a problem yeah that's
it unfortunately
you know it's baked into the current
operating system which is
hill climbing incrementalism right every
player
in the ai world has lots of incentives
to
make a move every quarter at least that
shows they're making progress
drive their market cap or the world's
perception of their importance etc
and usually the moves aren't that big
you know gpt-3 which is the buzz in ai
at the moment it's a pretty good sized
move but it's not huge but it's
incremental and nobody stops to really
think
what a whole series of incremental moves
over 10 years is going to result in
there is no meta system to evaluate
these kinds of risks and to keep people
from playing the
hill climber game theoretic game of
incremental moves
okay so this is interesting let's let's
look at kind of the
ascendancy or return to power depending
upon the perspective you want to take
that china's going through and the kind
of um
increasing fragmentation and descendancy
you can
see uh in the u.s
descendancy and coherence at least
so term limits make long-term planning
quite difficult
and we know why we like term limits was
we didn't want people to
to get too much power and corruption and
start thinking dynastically
of foreign by the people rotating but it
also does create an incentive for people
to do stuff
where either for their re-election or
simply for their new economic
opportunities getting out or the way
that they're
judged they're only going to be oriented
to do stuff that will create positive
return within the time of their term
limit
obviously it's even a shorter time limit
for directors
of corporations that have quarterly
decision profit cycles
and so a dynastic monarchy
that is thinking not only about the
person's whole life but about their
kids can actually do better long-term
planning and
if i have left versus right differences
where
when anyone does something for four
years the next four years somebody will
undo it
it's also and whatever the internal
coordination costs of the disagreement
are
so high it's also very hard to unify
enough to do stuff which is why the us
has had a hard time fixing its
infrastructure since the 50s and china
has built
high-speed trains all around the world
and so for a lot of reasons we can say
wow monarchy dynastic monarchy is just a
better system
because getting a lot of people to
coordinate
is really really hard and having someone
that can do long-term planning
uh be able to actually implement with
some coherence because there's not much
internal descent
seems like a better system and that
system can check its own ai
that system can do a lot of things
whereas the system where all the
companies are competing against each
other in a quarterly way and the parties
are competing against each other
seems to be stuck on a multi-polar trap
governed
situation and so this is i actually know
a lot of people who've
thought about multipolar traps a lot
whose only answer is we actually return
to monarchy and most of them think a
global monarchy run by a benevolent
aging
and so i think if we
right now it's pretty easy to see that
if the us continues the
kind of left right and all the divides
that it has
its shaping of the world continues to
decrease in relevance
probably china's continues to grow and
we see that
not just china but like turkey and
venezuela and brazil and a lot of places
have moved
to less participatory more autocratic
style of governance i think we lose the
21st century to that
and while that is because it's more
effective in a bunch of ways
and i think the only way to be able to
have something like a republic or a
participatory governance be more
effective
is if the many coordinating with each
other actually produces higher quality
results
than just a few being able to control
the thing and that's only going to
happen if it can harvest the collective
intelligence
and there actually really is some high
collective intelligence and now this
comes back to your
metamodern question do i think that we
can get the
hierarchical complexity or the ability
of people to process information
up yes even before that if i can start
getting them a memetic immune system to
where they aren't just
cognitively and emotionally hijacked
right now it's mostly not even
can they do good epistemology it's that
they're just captured by narrative
warfare
if i can simply get a memetic immune
system where people start to notice
how ruptural conjugation and lachoff
framing happens yes that
scientific article said something but
the news article
put spin on it can they notice how the
spin's occurring
yes that's a true statistic but it's
cherry picked when you look at all the
other statistics it doesn't look like
that same picture at all
and people start noticing those kind of
info and narrative weapons
and become inoculated enough that it's
not like
absolute lowest common denominator
collective intelligence
that will make a huge shift so we have
to factor the kind of
mimetic emotional immunity and cognitive
immunity
topic then better epistemology for the
individuals
and better orientation towards
socratic dialogue hegelian dialectic
like
seeking shared understanding because of
understanding the need to coordinate
being less bad than warfare not
coordinating
then i think we start to get emergent
collective intelligence where
more sovereign and intelligent people
and better conversations
start to produce systems of coordination
to bottom-up effect where those systems
of coordination produce a top-down
effect
that continues to incentivize that
bottom-up effect better and you get a
recursive process
between better systems of collective
sense making and choice making
and better development of individuals
and their communication capacity with
each other
yeah that's a beautiful picture but it's
got to fight hyper normal stimulation
right how does it escape that trap
well that's one of the immune systems
that i'm talking about how do we
how do we fight the trap of group
identity
that's a hard one there's a
courage required to not agree with the
thing where my friends are saying
silence is complicity and you're either
with us or against us
to actually be willing to be honest and
say i'm not sure i haven't looked at the
statistics i
haven't made good enough sense of this
requires a kind of profound
courage and epistemic commitment the
ability to mistrust my own
certainty realizing like this is one of
the insights that kind of really got me
into this was
i was certain about things where i later
realized i was wrong enough times that i
became very dubious of my own certainty
and then i recognized i'm clear
where i think a lot of other people
are wrong and i'm clear where almost
everyone historically believes stuff
fervently that i'm pretty sure they were
wrong about
flat earth or which god is true or
whatever
and i'm clear where i was wrong in the
past
but there isn't a single belief that i
hold now that i can say that i'm
probably wrong about even though
statistically i'm probably wrong about
most of them
and that when i go forward into the
future there will probably be some i
recognize that asymmetry is really
problematic and this is what got me to
start wanting to calculate what is my
basis for belief and what is the
confidence margin
and where do i believe things more
fervently because
it's a good story and i get to sound
smart or i get to be part of a group
or because it gives me security and how
can i start to have
a psychology that is more independent of
those things
so my belief system is not bolstering me
identity wise or existentially
so that's a kind of psychological
emotional mimetic social immune process
that has to be part of the enlightenment
we're talking about and so basically i'm
saying
participatory governance is hard
autocracy is
just easier for a bunch of reasons
either we should start designing the
monarchies we want to be part of
or participatory governance only ever
emerged out of
and was successful as long as there was
a cultural enlightenment that made it
possible so we either
have to re-drive a cultural
enlightenment to be able to revivify
participatory governance
or we should start steering the kind of
autocracy we want
and that might the enlightenment we want
to drive is not
just a cognitive enlightenment it is the
susceptibility to hypernormal stimuli
it is a value system around
uh respectful engagement with other
people and seeking their points of view
it's
it's all those things together yep let
me hit on a couple of
point topics then i'm going to turn it
over to you because i know you've
thought about this more than most
what are the next moves that need to be
done but first let's hit
on two other topics one we talked
earlier about bad faith discourse and
then you alluded to the fact that
you know not only is there bad faith
this course but there's good faith
discourse
that's just wrong and i will say that
our current
evolved information infrastructure seems
to
have produced an evolutionary context
which produces some very
virulent forms of being wrong you know
anti-vaxxer being
an interesting one right it's like what
the 100 people have died from bad
vaccines in the united states since 1950
millions have been saved how could this
even be an issue and yet
evolutionarily a memeplex has been
created that has attracted millions and
millions of people
q anon is another interesting one a
classic example of a
evolved artifact that you know by any
objective measure just seems
insane
and yet not only do millions of people
believe parts of it
hundreds of thousands at least seem to
have it as a main hobby in their life
trying to do the research figure out the
clues etc
and so something i guess i would point
out compared to 1965
you were not going to see either
anti-vaxxers or q anon
on the cbs evening news with walter
cronkite
the gatekeepers of that era if nothing
else we're good at keeping absolute
nonsense
out of widespread public circulation
then the second point which you just hit
on
is tribalism seems to be what we fall
back
on when we're so overwhelmed by an
information
evolved platform which is driven by bad
incentives
plus complexity plus scale and we now
just say
throw up our hands and say it i
can't figure it out so i'm team blue
whatever team blue believes i'll believe
i'm team red whatever team red
believes i'll believe we've all seen
those big posters with all the
logical fallacies on them i've come to
believe that this epoch
of tribalism has made one logical
fallacy dominant all
over the rest and that's confirmation
bias
everything i hear i would say not me i'm
the one exception but let's say the
laughing here ironically that you know
the mass people who are in the tribes
they compare every fact or item they
hear
against what's the tribal take on all
this rather than trying to look at
something objectively
and decide whether they should believe
it or not so
daniel what can be and should be done
starting tomorrow morning what do we do
should we start at the level of what
individuals can do on their own
or what we could do to try to attack
these issues
project wise i would suggest a bit of
both
and what's of course best is where
project wise cycles back to the
individual and then back to the project
but go with what you think is the
priorities
i want to just say one thing first and
this is a funny thing to say but
um if we talk about anti-backs or q anon
or any particular view like that
i can really empathize with
those and i think it's important that
everyone can
because i think most people
sense that there are a lot of things
wrong with the world
and moving towards catastrophically
worse
that those who are in most power both
uh politically and financially don't
seem to be doing a good job with though
they seem to
be increasing in their own personal
wealth or power or whatever else
so there's a sense of corruption that
most everyone senses it's just then they
want to fit it into very simplistic
narratives where there's good guys and
bad guys and they can be on team good
and that kind of thing so the right all
thinks that the left's news is fake
and the left thinks that the rights news
is fake they each think that the other
ones politicians are corrupt
so the idea that politicians could be
corrupt or news could be fake
well that's actually true it's just
not true that it falls just along those
partisan lines it's more that you've got
to understand
as for anyone to ascend the stack of
power they have to do well at the game
of power and there's a lot of things
that that involves to do well at the
game of power
and so i think the idea that there's are
these institutional authorities and we
should just totally trust them
has pretty much broken you were
mentioning you know in 1965
in 1965 the people who were alive paying
attention to the news
directly remembered world war ii in
their life experience right
and that had a a kind of unifying basis
a patriotic
um and unifying basis and an empirical
basis we had to really double down on
science and technology to uh be able to
win the war and
but then there starts to be an
institutional decay where not that many
people who are live paying attention to
the news now
or very large numbers of them weren't
around in world war ii
and they don't have any real embodied
sense of what breakdown in the developed
world
could look like and so similarly they
have much more sense of the enemy that
is near than the enemy that is far and
those types of things
and then when we so when we look at
vaccines for instance
it's actually a bit of a complex topic
because
if you're making something that is a
drug that's intended to have long-term
effects as opposed to most small
molecule drugs that stop
acting after they've left your body
could they have long-term
consequences and if we've done mostly
the studies on individual
vaccines and yet they're given in
schedules with lots of them
together do we really know what the
collective effect of that much immune
modulation long-term unlocks them
together is
and if at the same time that they've
been going up polio and whatever's been
going down but hygiene and antibiotics
have
also been happening during that time and
then autoimmune disease and other things
like that seem to be going up
is the autoimmune disease and the
infertility going up because of the
vaccines or is it going up because of
the glyphosate or ubiquitous
environmental toxins or stress
those are actually complex topics and so
it's very easy to say all vaccines are
bad
or all vaccines are good anti-vaxxers
are stupid and neither of those are
complex enough to actually make good
sense of it
but the need to take a very strong
position because the
the other view is so bad and dangerous
we have to fight it
ends up being the tribalism confirmation
bias and so
and then people only have a pejorative
straw man or even worse a villainized
version of the other
they they can't even imagine how anyone
could be that stupid or bad as to
believe that thing
and of course you can't have
participatory governance when that's how
you think about the other people you're
supposedly part of a republic with
um or part of a civilization at all with
so where people start to doubt the
institutional authority
there's something good in that but then
oftentimes what happens is rather than
really learn the epistemology needed to
make sense of it they just
jump to the new authority and usually
the new authority is whoever it is
that's telling them
to doubt the other one and so that's
inadequate they're not actually moving
up
vertically into more hierarchical
complexity they're just shifting
authorities
i just wanted to say that as preface
yeah that's i think that's a good
preface and i'll i will confess that
i'm a real knee-jerker on anti-vaxxer
have i done enough research to be
absolutely sure about it no
and so i will plead to a little bit of
tribalism on that one in fact
it's the only topic which i have at
least when i was running the show
over in raleigh point alpha the only
topic i which i
banned discourse on was anti-vaxxer so
make opa continue so
um and this is tricky because let's say
a new person is coming into a topic that
has been very well addressed but they
don't know
do the people who've well addressed it
have to re-go through it every time
that's actually a tricky topic right
from the good use of time point of view
so in terms of collective intelligence
if a group has done
really earnest dialectic to come to a
certain confidence margin on something
the path there not just the conclusion
but the path there
should be left in some intact way that
other people can walk
and then if someone has critiques that
are
legitimate object level critiques of the
actual path there the conclusions we
should listen
and that's i think how science can
continue to evolve
is where we can continue to critique our
best understanding
and have dissent around it without
having to repeat the things that have
actually been done well many times
okay so your question what do we do
tomorrow at the level of the individual
forgive me i'm going to make a religious
reference the
commandment in the bible to not have any
false idols
the way that i take that i take it very
similarly to the first verse of the tao
te ching
um so i think a lot of cultures said
something wisdom-wise and maybe
maybe i'm just reading it the way i want
to read it so no false idols
any model i make of reality isn't
reality it's me trying to
info compress the complexity of reality
into some
small number of variables and operators
on those variables where i can model the
outcome with hopefully enough numerical
accuracy that it's useful so this is the
all models are
wrong some of them are useful the moment
i make a model truth
now i'm not in direct relationship with
reality anymore i'm in
relationship with the simulacra and so
the idol of the models that i have of
reality i want to hold them as useful
and see which ones are more useful while
never
actually having any identity attached to
them
never having any sense of sacredness
attached to them because i know that
better ones will come along
and i want to be seeking those so if
people can
like deepen their commitment to a direct
relationship with reality which
binds them to a certain amount of
uncertainty
and as a result be dubious of being over
devoted to any models of reality
that's very helpful like as almost like
a sacred oath at the foundation of it
and then if that's the case that's what
will motivate them
to be dubious of their own cognitive
biases and emotional traps and when they
feel very outraged and when they feel
very certain and when they feel
a very clear repulsion to a group that
seems obviously bad or a very clear
identity with an in-group
they should just be dubious of all of
that and step back and say
what's the chance and what are the
possibilities that i'm being emotionally
or cognitively hijacked and i'm not
seeing the whole thing
if people can just start to actually
have a bias checker in themselves as
a as a value as a discipline because
they want to be in better
connection with reality and truth and
they
know that more than more than anything
else it's their own misassessment of it
to check
that's very helpful then they can start
to learn
tools that will help them of like okay
let me actually
learn some of how narrative warfare
works let me understand
how russell conjugation is used by the
left and the right
or how like off framing is used in
marketing and on all sides let me see
how
cherry picking of data works and how
the funding of science works in a way
that makes the preponderance of data not
necessarily fit the whole picture
as i start to learn that more i start to
be less manipulated
by what occurs in the media environment
and also simultaneously i want to seek
dissenting views that seem earnest on
everything
so when you are mentioning that you will
seek people that know more than you
about a topic i will try to seek the
people that i think
know the most and who disagree but who
seem in good faith about their
disagreement because
the dialectic between them i i have more
faith in than i do
in either of the positions singularly
held
and so if i can see where the ipcc has a
standard model on climate change but
both
james lovelock on one side and freeman
dyson on the other side
have done quite thoughtful analysis and
come to different conclusions
i want to say do i understand why each
of them came to the conclusions they do
well
can i facilitate a dialogue between
those perspectives to try to
maybe have more epistemic flexibility
and come to better
understanding so these are just a you
know examples of a few things
individuals can do on their own
one of the things that looks like is
just obviously
remove the social media apps from your
phone so you don't have a continuous
drip of micro targeting
and if you keep it on your computer at
all
curate your own feed so that you're
using it as a tool more and it's using
you less
so unfollow all of the things that
you're automatically following that
are not actually enhancing your sense
making and then intentionally follow
things that represent
different views on every topic so there
are
far left moderate left moderate right
far right conspiracy theorist
other countries views on every topic i
follow
because i want to get the parallax on
all those views one because i want to
understand why
huge amounts of humanity are thinking
those things and two i want to make sure
i'm not missing anything where there's
partial signal in what they're saying
okay those are good let me respond here
a little bit let's start with social
media
you missed one which i think is key i
had rene derista
on the podcast yesterday she's a
researcher at
stanford on social media exploits by bad
actors mostly and
she pointed out the one thing that we
could all do
is ask ourselves three times before we
share
something is this actually good for the
world to share
this right because what you read is
important but we're also
in social media we are actors in the
formation of the epistemic commons
and when we share something or like on a
reddit platform
we upvote something or like something we
are making a
shaping of the commons and so at that
point think three times before you act
at all
i would suggest that's useful and now in
terms of here
we pivot to more institutional things i
would also like to comment that okay
yeah i understand that if we really want
to think through climate change
fully and understand you know built-in
biases
you know where are the error bars etc
it's very good to start
with love luck on one side dyson in the
middle and a bunch of guys in between
process all that data and come to some
conclusion on what might be true and
what the error bars actually
are but let me tell you that's a job
over the pay grade of almost every
single human
being and maybe if i did nothing else
for two years i might be able to do that
realistically i don't see very many
people being able to process
high scale high complexity issues in
that kind of way
which then pivots me to what can be done
institutionally or as artifacts or in
groups to accomplish the same thing so
that people can consume
the result of a process like that
well as you know i'm part of a group
that's working on
building a project to try to do some of
this and so i can tell you the thing
that we're trying to do that compared to
the scope of the entire information
ecology
and the algorithmic bias uh on these
major platforms what we're doing is
actually pretty
small and humble compared to everything
that needs to happen but
it's the highest leverage easiest to
achieve things i'm aware of
uh as a starting place to then hopefully
be able to
have more stuff come so for instance
let's take that particular topic the
climate change one
there's both how do we make sense of the
realities of climate change then there's
how do we make sense of the right choice
for climate change factoring the
adjacent issues like u.s china issues
and other geopolitical issues and market
issues and things like that
so one of the things that we're doing is
in this project that is trying to kind
of
upgrade and fix the media ecology and uh
remove the effectiveness of the
narrative and info weapons by pointing
them out so as we make
the covert things overt they have
uh more ability to be resisted
so hosting not debates
but dialectic conversations between the
best thinkers on topics
who are earnest who are willing to
engage in a non-rhetorical authentic
kind of sense-making process together
and who disagree
where the facilitator is both
skilled in dialectical facilitation but
also understands the topic well enough
to be able to facilitate it between
these people who understand it
exceptionally well and represent the
variants and views and if someone is
oriented to just want to win a debate or
be rhetorical we don't invite them on
they'd have to agree to the
um kind of dialectic process and then we
do things like well what do we all agree
on
like what what is known what is unknown
do we agree on what's known do we agree
on what things are unknown and then
do we have a different weighting on the
things that we think are known
or unknown but have some probability on
why do we have those
weightings that lead to why we have
different senses of things
and so can the can the listener who's
watching this
see what the how the best thinkers think
about it see where the differences are
see where they should have some
certainty and where there's
where there's uncertainty and get up to
kind of the best
general sense of where the topic is at
we're
doing one of those right now with uh
different experts on
immunity looking at what is likely to
occur for covet immunity long term
and so topics that are both
consequential and
uh debated being able to facilitate a
process like that that's one example
and so this does like you said make it
where if it's beyond the pay grade of a
person
can we make an institution that is doing
that that doesn't have any other
institutional incentive doesn't have a
economic uh or political or whatever
kind of bias
and is really seeking to simply be a
steward of the information commons and
is making their process transparent
enough
that it can be held to that and then
things
so like one of the things that another
kind of
thing that we're working on is for any
topic that is highly
polarized but also trending and
consequential where
it's not just that we can't solve it if
we don't have a shared understanding but
where the disagreement itself becomes a
source
of open violence in the streets which
has obviously gotten worse in
recently than it has been in recent
history and can get much more worse
moving forward if we're not
um very effective at changing that
trajectory
so one of the things is pick a topic and
we do this kind of meta news so uh
an assessment of the landscape of
narratives sometimes there's really
just two narratives left and right one
that are dominant but sometimes there's
like
seven narratives that are really
trending that are really fundamentally
different from each other
so do an assessment of here's the
primary narratives in the landscape
here's a number of different kind of
publications or news sources
that are clustered together kind of
pushing each of these
and then let's actually steel men each
one let's kind of make the best argument
for it
so that people who don't believe that
narrative
can see why some other people who do
believe it are compelled by it and have
a version of other people that is not
just
um villainizing then
and where people are starting to learn
to seek other people's perspectives and
learn to steelman them
and then an analytic process that so
that first process is kind of
intersubjective the next one is
objective can we break the narrative
into individual propositions
and can we try to see what evidence was
put forward to support the propositions
and then can we look at
all the rest of the evidence we can find
that either support or refute them
and what we'll then do is find where is
their identifiable signal
in all of the positions and then where
are there clearly falsifiable things
and then where is there a bunch of stuff
that has to sit as neither falsifiable
nor
verifiable currently is just conjecture
for which we should have no confidence
one way or the other
and so this is this process as people go
through it helps them
do things like learn propositional logic
learn how to break down a narrative and
not reject or accept the whole thing but
be able to see there's probably some
signal probably some noise and a lot of
conjecture
and how to calibrate their confidence
margins and then
how to step back and say based on the
things that we can identify that are
true across these spaces across these
narratives what can we probably say
about the space as a whole
which is a synthesizing process where
the earlier one was a
analysis process so there's a kind of
interpersonal narrative intelligence
then an analytic empirical intelligence
than a synthesizing intelligence all of
which are needed to make sense so
if we can do that with people that get
highly trained in that and it's their
full-time job to do
but then also walk people through the
steps it'll help them make sense of
what's going on and just
understand why the conflict is there and
diffuse the conflict
and then also show where each of the
different sources are
employing whether it's intentional or
not
narrative and info weapons show where
they're putting spin on things of what
the original thing
that was true was and then the way they
framed it show where they're doing
statistical cherry picking and if they
looked at these other statistics
how it would change the overall picture
so that people start noticing the
narrative and info weapons and not being
and they start to look for them
and they look for them across the
political spectrum um an ideological
spectrum
rather than just in a tribal way if we
can do that for people but also
walk them through the steps of how we're
doing it so they learn how to do it on
their own if we stopped being
able to do it they could keep doing it
these are examples of
processes that i think can help upgrade
the info ecology quite a bit
also when we're doing kind of the news
itself just base sense making on a topic
before we look at the meta news of how
everybody else is sense making or
representing it
when we say what we're able to assess
we'll also show our process of
what data are we factoring and what
epistemic models are we including
so if someone wants to see how did we
come to that how did we calculate our
confidence they can see it and then they
can learn the epistemic models
so can we make it to where you know you
and i both know that understanding
tainter helps in the way we understand
a lot of things in the world or
understanding mcluhan or gerard or
bayesian analysis
things that people didn't get and
they're not going to go read all the
books to get them can we
just compress the epistemic
models into the shortest kinds of essays
that then
also show how to apply them and give
sense making reifying power
and then link them where they're useful
so that people can
start to increase it's almost like an
optimized public education and how to
make sense of the world that will
empower civic engagement
so these are these are some examples of
basically how do we start to
do a kind of broadcast where people
aren't trusting it because of
some authority they're trusting their
own ability to make sense of reality
better because we're showing the
transparent process and we're increasing
their epistemic capacity and not just
making
sense of based reality but also making
sense of the way it's being represented
in the narrative landscape
i think that this has the ability if
we're successful and
to start de-arming the effectiveness of
the narrative and info weapons and the
tribalism and the outrage certainty
and increasing people's own epistemic
capabilities
then if that becomes a strange attractor
for a group of people that are attracted
to that who start to also engage in
higher quality
conversation you start to get a cultural
attractor that could become very
meaningful
ah it sounds really good i really hope
you're able to get this
going and then i think then there's a
second order effect and third order
effect
which is if these artifacts that are
created are compelling
and have sufficient production values
that they can spread
virally and memetically then they can
compete in the idea marketplace and
perhaps push back some
less well-formed ideas yeah and i would
say even more excited
than viral sharing because viral sharing
is mostly not thinking right
it's just being memetic repeaters um and
i know you and jordan have talked about
this uh you know simulated thinking but
for the most part people especially in
say the facebook environment aren't
actually thinking they're just
looking at a thing and saying does this
conforms to my current thinking ideas
that i should repeat it or not and if it
does then i hit
you know share or whatever so most
people are just acting as kind of
memetic filters and propagators we're
thinking would be
is this true what are the other opinions
how do i know what kind of deeper
process do i do research is just the
vetting is it true thinking is also
not just looking externally but looking
internally at
what is meaningful about this how would
i go about making sense of this
and so while viral replication has some
value
i would actually hope that a success of
what we would do would be
eventually the end of viral replication
in that way
and instead say some people who started
to get
much better at facilitating high quality
dialogue at facilitating
dialectical thinking and steel manning
different positions as well as
empiricism
and those people become parts of
everybody's friend group and just start
to facilitate not just we're sharing
this piece of content
but we're facilitating authentically
better conversation in all these other
environments
yeah i think that's good but i also
think it's a little bit wishful thinking
i suspect because of the issues of the
distributions of hierarchical complexity
the number of people who can really
deeply think about these
large-scale complex issues is small but
there'll be some number that can engage
in it and having more engaged in real
thinking and
modeling real thinking as opposed to
simulated thinking
will also help up regulate the
credibility of the artifacts for people
who are going to be consumers rather
than thinkers for themselves
but this sounds like really exciting
stuff i look forward to
watching you guys progress and i think
on that note we should wrap it up we're
over our
normal timeline but this has been such a
fascinating and interesting discussion
as it always is with daniel so thanks
for coming on board and sharing your
thoughts
this was fun thank you for uh this
sense-making
platform that you have shared so much
with for everybody and having me on
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared james consulting
music by tom muller at modern space
music